<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections on a dialogue between a Calvinistical preacher and a thief wherein is shewn the unreasonableness of the Calvinistical decrees.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58349</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13651008</idno>
  <idno type="VID">100985</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248502919</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33985</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13651008</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58349)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100985)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1045:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections on a dialogue between a Calvinistical preacher and a thief wherein is shewn the unreasonableness of the Calvinistical decrees.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Wells ... and sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Calvinism --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS ON A DIALOGUE BETWEEN A Calvinistical Preacher AND A THIEF: Wherein is shewn the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness of the <hi>Calvinisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Decrees.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Lege, antequam judicas.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Wells,</hi> near the West-end of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> and Sold by the Booksellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HAVING read a Book, Entituled, <hi>A Dialogue between a</hi> Calvinistical <hi>Preacher and a Thief:</hi> Who notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Evils which he had done, did yet think himself pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinated to Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>The unusualness of the Subject inclin'd me to Translate it, upon which I propos'd my intent to some of my Acquaintance; who, perswaded me to do it, but sind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Book upon the account of its Impiety not fit to be translated, without such Reflections upon the
<pb facs="tcp:100985:3"/>Discourse of the Thief and Preacher, as might be useful to hinder the farther spreading of their wicked Opinions, instead therefore of a formal Translation which I once design'd, I shall do what I suppose will be more for your advantage, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> I will Historically repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the Thiefs Arguments, and the Preachers Answers.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I will shew that the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Answers are not sufficient to bring the Thief from the Impiety which he had lived in.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I will endeavour to give such an account of the Divine Decrees as may (through God's goodness) prevent others falling into the like horrid Opinions, and this I shall endeavour to do these two ways.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> By proving that an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute, immutable and unconditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Decree, is inconsistent with the Divine Goodness.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> By shewing that such a Decree would destroy all true Piety.</p>
            <p>This Method I am inclin'd to take for these two Reasons.</p>
            <p>First because the mischief of the Thiefs Notions might farther extend its self, if he was only made to speak <hi>English.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, because I have been inform'd that the <hi>Fur Praedesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> hath been already Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but whether it hath or no, this Method I hope will make the ensuing Discourse useful to you, for whose good I design'd it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:4"/>
            <p>Tho' the Doctrine of an immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, absolute and unconditional Decree, be indeed abominable; and tho' according to these <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistical</hi> Principles, a Man cannot be converted, because he may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse the great Impiety of his Life, by the greater Impiety of his Faith; nowithstanding the Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of the Doctrine, there are many besides the Preacher and the Thief, who have adopted these Principles into their Religion and Creed. Therefore in order to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the farther spreading of them, I shall <hi>in transitu</hi> make some Reflections upon the Thiefs Arguments, and the Preachers Answers; least an uninterrupted Series of Blasphemy, might with an unwary Reader make these Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines pass for good Divinity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:4"/>
            <p>The vileness of the Doctrine hath met with Men vile enough to defend it, and therefore I have endeavour'd to expose it, that we may not be forced to feel its evil Effects, which that we may not, is the prayer of him who is kind Reader,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:5"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100985:5"/>
            <head>Reflections on a <hi>Dialogue</hi> between a <hi>Cavinistical</hi> Preacher and a Thief.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A Calvinistical</hi> Preacher hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Thief condemn'd to dye for the Crimes he he had Committed, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Impiousness of his Life, and the Evils which he had done, was yet so confident as to think himself Predestinated to Eternal Life comes to visit him that he might know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his hopes of his <hi>Predestination</hi> were well grounded, and that the Thief might not ruine himself in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100985:6"/>World, as he had already done in this; the Preacher enquires into the State and Condition of his Soul, which that he might know, he thus begins his Discourse,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A good Evening to you young Man, How do you live?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which Question the Thief Answer'd, <hi>That he had liv'd as it had pleased God, who works all Things according to the pleasure of his own Will, to determine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, and in time to effect in him,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preacher hearing this Answer of the Thief, told him <hi>that he said true, and that he was much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to see him in Chains,</hi> telling the Thief, <hi>that he ought much more to be troubled, for his sad State and Condition, for that now a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable Death was soon to period and end all the Extravagancies, and Follies of his past Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100985:6"/>
            <p>To which the Thief Replys, <hi>that he knew not why the Preacher or himself should be troubled for his present Circumstances, because he did not know but that tho' he had not long to live in the World, yet that he might by an absolute immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and unconditional Decree be Predestinated to the eternal happi- of the next.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here Reader you may find the Thief giving himself (notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his wicked Life) a very fair Character, and instead of deploring his sinful Life, and with sighs and tears begging the pardon of it, he speaks with no more concern either for his present or future Interest, than if he had been already possest of all those Glories to the enjoyment of which, he vainly supposed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self Predestinated.</p>
            <p>Tho' this extravagant and impious Discourse of the Thief did justly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the Preachers reproof, yet he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100985:7"/>doth not blame the Thief either for the impiousness of his Life, or the no concern which he had for his Interest in another World, which ought now to have been provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, because his aboad was to be so short in this; yet here is no sense of Sorrow in the Thief, nor no Exhortations to Repentance from the Preacher, but as if he came rather to secure the Thief in his Sins than to bring him from them, the Preacher grants <hi>that the Thief had lived according to God's Will,</hi> which one <hi>postulatum</hi> granted was I think more powerful to keep the Thief in his Sins, than any thing that the Preacher could say to disswade him from them.</p>
            <p>For to live <hi>according to God's Will</hi> is certainly the best Life, not only in reference to the Piety but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so the Advantage of it; because <hi>the Will of God</hi> is the rule of all that is good; God being in his own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100985:7"/>so perfectly Good that he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth nor can Will that which is Evil, and therefore the Thief did no less falsly than blasphemously Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm <hi>that he had liv'd according to God's Will:</hi> This impious assertion of the Thief <hi>that he had lived ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Will</hi> would (if right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consider'd) have been as Insignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant as it was Impious; is through the Preachers Impious Confession become unanswerable; for to grant that the Thief notwithstanding the Evils which he had done, <hi>had lived according to God's Will,</hi> was but in effect to applaud him for his Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, to commend him for his Vices, and to encourage him to be damn'd: Whereas if he had told the Thief that that he did miserably deceive himself to think <hi>that he lived according to God's Will,</hi> whilst he violated his Commandments, one of which was, <hi>thou shalt not Steal,</hi> and that to the breach of this Commandment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100985:8"/>God had threatned the loss of the Kingdom of Heaven, which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doth to those <hi>who do his Will,</hi> no, they are always happy in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; which if he did expect to be, he must repent of his Sins, for that it was not only a false but also a dangerous supposition, <hi>that he did God's Will</hi> whilst he sinned against him, for that it was impossible for him to do <hi>God's Will,</hi> when he had in so many Instances violated his Laws; to the violation of which Laws, God had threatned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted too so many punishments even in this Life, that he could not but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire that notwithstanding the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples he had imbibed, his Sins did not sometimes sit uneasie on his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, since he always in his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory carryed a witness against him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self which could not but make him fear (inspight of all his evil Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) least his Faith should do him more hurt in another World, than his Life had done in this.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100985:8"/>
            <p>Tho' the Thief did believe <hi>that he had lived according to God's Will,</hi> and the Preacher did grant <hi>that he had,</hi> yet to me it seems im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible that he should not know that in each violation of <hi>God's Law,</hi> he did live contrary to his <hi>Will.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less that at last he should not only loose his Conscience, but also his Sense and Reason too, and so at once become so extravagantly foolish and wicked, as to suppose God to be actually as well as permissively the Cause of Evil; falsely deeming the Almighty to be no less the Author of our Sins than Life: And that it was equally pleasing to him whether we lead innocent or vitious lives; thus as some Men take their Faith from their Sins, so these take their Sins from their Faith.</p>
            <p>This belief makes the Thief speak as confidently of his State and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as if he had not done amiss; And I am sure the Preacher's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100985:9"/>doth not tend to bring him from his Evil Sentiments, of the Divine Decrees; for the Preacher having once granted <hi>that the Thief had lived according to God's Will,</hi> did thereby make useless and render in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual all his after Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>For 'tis to no purpose to perswade that Man to live holily who is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready assured <hi>that he lives according to God's Will;</hi> for if God doth Will only that which is Good, as both Reason and Religion do oblige us to believe, then to diswade a Man from doing of <hi>God's Will,</hi> would be so far from being a duty, that it would be a Sin; and one might just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suppose all such diswasions to be the Teachings of a Fiend, and of one sent from the Regions of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in order to bring Men there, rather than of a Preacher of the Gospel sent to perswade Men from their Evil Ways. But on the other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100985:9"/>side, if <hi>God Wills</hi> that which is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, how can he be just in punishing us for the doing of that which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self hath oblig'd us to do? So that this concession was as dishonourable to God, as it was destructive to the Thief, and may more justly be thought a perverting of the Gospel, than it can be a Preaching of it.</p>
            <p>Had the Thief indeed <hi>lived ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Command,</hi> the Preachers pity would have been as useless as his Arguments; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Thiefs being in Chains or shortly to dye ought to have been a trouble either to the Thief, or Preacher, or any other Spectator of his Death; for that <hi>if he had dyed according to God's Will,</hi> he must have been a Martyr, which would have been a great joy to think that he was by Sufferings to be tormented to Death, to dye into eternal Life, that at the Resurrection he might rise with the more honour, and have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100985:10"/>his seeming disgraceful Death re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced with real and everlasting Pleasures: And certainly however sad his Sufferings might appear to those, whose hopes were only in this Life; yet to those whose Faith had enabled them to look beyond the Grave, and as were to anticipate the happiness of the next Life, by their practising the holiness of it in this.</p>
            <p>They who by a well-lead Life did in and through Christ expect the Joys of the next, are willing at any rate to enjoy the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to these the thoughts of the cause of his Death, would have made it lovely, in spight of all the ugly Shapes and Forms the most cruel Tormentors can dress it in: So that the nobleness of the Cause of his dying would have so far sanctified the Act as to have made it valued and desired, as that which was at once his highest Honour and greatest Felicity.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100985:10"/>
            <p>The Primitive Christians were so far from deeming that Death dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable which was suffered for the sake of Christ and the Gospel, that they became Candidates for it, and thought it an honour not only to do the <hi>Will of God,</hi> but also to suffer for the doing it. For those purer times of Christianity were more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and Holy, than either to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themselves or to teach others that to live wickedly was to do the <hi>Will of God,</hi> there was then no Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Dort</hi> called to debauch Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, under pretence of defending it. This Doctrine being too vile for any but a <hi>Calvinist</hi> to teach, or for any but a Thief to believe.</p>
            <p>And tho' it seems strange that any Man should teach such Doctrines, yet I think it more strange that others should believe them; for they are too absurd to be embrac'd by any, but those who are as much Debauched in their Intellectuals, as Morals, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100985:11"/>I should think this Doctrine a libel upon the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> were there not too many Books as well as Men, to patronize and defend it even to this day.</p>
            <p>I cannot but admire that any Man should be so fond as to think that he can perswade another that he doth <hi>the Will of God</hi> whilst he Acts those Sins to the Commission of which God hath threatned eternal Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
            <p>How is it possible to perswade Men to a good Life? When they have been taught that their Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth entirely depend upon their <hi>Predestination,</hi> which being unconditional and immutable no Power of Man can reverse it, nor any religious Duty do that Man any good, who is by these Decrees as much excluded from Holiness, as he is from Happiness.</p>
            <p>The Thief finding a holy Life so little advantageous to him in another
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100985:11"/>World, doth notwithstanding his bad Circumstances and worse Life infer to himself comfort from the Preachers grant, <hi>that he had lived according to God's Will,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tho the baseness of the Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he now suffered for the Evils he had done, might justly mind him of the greater baseness of his Crimes; and tho' he might daily see in the Chams which he wore about him, the loss of his Liberty, and did expect that the loss of his Life would soon follow that of his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; yet the very thoughts of his living <hi>according to God's Will</hi> do so comfort him in his Sufferings, that he shews no concern either for his present or future Interest, but seems as well pleas'd as if no Evil either had or should befall him.</p>
            <p>He therefore upon the Preachers desire to know how he had lived, (that he might the better know how to direct his Conscience, and be able
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100985:12"/>to determine whether eternal Joys or everlasting Misery was like to be the Thiefs final Portion) makes as free a Confession of his Sins, as if he had been only giving an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent History of his Life, relating his Villanies with as little regret as he committed them, giving the Preacher this following Relation of of his Life, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That from his tender Years his Parents did instruct him in Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and intended to send him to the</hi> University, <hi>but being doubtful where to send him because</hi> Leiden University <hi>was thought Heretical,</hi> Frankford <hi>was deem'd as full of Gladiators and Drunkards, as</hi> Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>of Hereticks, both of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangerous, the one for its He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies, the other for its Impieties; at last the thoughtful Parents by the Advice of their Preacher send their Son to</hi> Frankford <hi>supposing it less dangerous to breed him among
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100985:12"/>Sword Players and Drunkards, than Hereticks. After he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Parents blessing he goes to</hi> Frankford, <hi>where he no sooner comes, but the excellency of the Wine, and the pleasantness of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he met with, made him soon consume all his Money in feasting, which his Parents hearing, and finding the Money which they did design for his improvement in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Arts, to be spent in Vice and Vanity, call him home, after which they sent him to</hi> France, <hi>where tho' he doth acknowledge that they lived soberly, yet the Sobriety of the Place, doth not prevail with him to comply with the Sobriety of the Inhabitants, but those Vices which he learnt at</hi> Frankford, <hi>he brought to</hi> France, <hi>were he was so extravagant, that he was almost always drunk, and had a Gentlewoman of Pleasure as seldome from his Lap, as a glass from his Lip.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100985:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In fine his Debauchees were too frequently acted, and too publickly committed to be long conceal'd from his Parents, whose concern for their Son's welfare, made them very inquisitive into his Conver sation, and finding that his change of Place had made none in his Life, they therefore determine to send him to</hi> Geneva, <hi>where least by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of his Vices he should be unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go, they threaten to allow him no Maintenance unless he would live there, hoping that the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noss of the Place would prevail with their Son to imitate the Sanctity of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Parents having been told by the Preacher that</hi> Geneva <hi>was a Holy Place, where Vice is so far from being allowed, that Dancing it self is forbidden there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Place so Holy, the credulous Parents (being imposed only by the Preacher) believe that their Son
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100985:13"/>would live in</hi> Geneva <hi>like another</hi> Samuel <hi>in the House of the Lord, hoping he would now become more exemplary for piety, than ever he had been for Debaucheries: His Parents therefore with great joy sent him there, where he no sooner comes but he meets with new incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to his former Impiety.</hi> viz. <hi>With a Land lady as beautiful and charming as</hi> Venus <hi>whose seeming Piety did as much forbid his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant thought and desires, as her Beauty did invite and encourage them the pretended sanctity of his Landlady made her seem a Saint, which obliged him for some time not to dare to attempt what at length he easily perpetrated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>After which, that the Thief might get the favour of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, he counterfeits the Saint in order to act the Devil, which that he might the better do, he seems to change his Life, and goes now
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100985:14"/>as zealously to the Church as he did formerly to the Tavern, he hears Sermons and the better to be taken notice off, he sits under the Pulpit, with a great Bible, fetching all the proofs which were cited by the Preacher, from which pretended sanctity having gain'd esteem, he lays aside the Person of a Saint, to act that of a noble Man, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Sword and keeping a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant who served him in a double capacity,</hi> viz. <hi>that of a Scrvaut and a Baud; who laying aside his Man's apparel, past for a femal, by wich means the Thief wanted nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wine nor Women Cards nor Dice, nor Birds sweetly singing, the more to endear that conversation which had already charmed him out of his Reputation and Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here Reader you have the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of some of the Thiefs impieties which he doth recount to the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with as little concern as he acted them at the hearing of which, the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100985:14"/>Preacher doth not reprove him, nor represent to him the sadness of his Condition, nor direct him how to get the pardon of those Sins in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World for which he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd in this. Yea this condition of the Thief so deplorable as it is, is yet no farther taken notice of by the Preacher, then to ask him this question, <hi>viz. that if he had known how severely he should have been punished for his Sins, whether he would have committed them, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in so Holy a Place as</hi> Geneva, <hi>where dancing which in some places is reckoned as an accomplishment is deem'd a fault?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Thief had experienced that, tho dancing in <hi>Geneva</hi> was counted an Offence, yet faults of a deeper dye were not so severely animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon; because that as great Crimes were there acted as in other Places, and therefore the Thief laying aside the Hypocrisie of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100985:15"/>Place tho' not the Villany, goes on with the Relation of his Impiety, saying, <hi>that he and his Companions after the Commission of many Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, which were too many to be conceal'd, and so notoriously ill that at length being brought before the Magistrate they were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son'd,</hi> upon which the Thief began to think that now all his luxurious living was to end in Troubles and Disgraces, which began now to sit heavy upon him, insomuch, that now he thinks himself as miserable as he was sinful, for that a sad Scene of Sorrows was to succeed to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Villanies; and all his choice Viands to be exchang'd for Bread and Water, Food tho' course and mean, yet too good for those who had Rioted with the blessings of Heaven, and affronted the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Mercies he had bestowed on them: Such thoughts as these did sometimes occasion the Thief to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100985:15"/>make melancholly Reflections upon his past Life, untill he and his Companions soon found that their usage was not so bad as they did deserve or fear, for that others who were guilty of the same or greater faults, were as kind to them as if they had been as much allyed in Blood, as they were in Villany, these Men whose Estates were almost as great as the Crimes they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, the bravery of whose Cloaths made them as much gazed at as the Evils they had done, these did by their Feasting, Dancing and other Pleasures render the Prison so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful that it became a place of Pleasure, rather than punishment, for such extravagancies were even here acted, that the Criminals did in a manner expiate their Crimes with as much pleasure as they did commit them, Dancing even to the shaking of the beams, and this they did while they were in Frison, a very
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100985:16"/>pleasant Confinement this, if it had been but as innocent as it was diverting.</p>
            <p>When the time of their Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ended, they were brought before the Consistory, who unbray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them the baseness of their Crimes, after which in a full As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly they were forced to lie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate before the Pulpit, and to ask God and the Church pardon for the Scandal which they had given, this being done the disgrace ended with the punishment, for at <hi>Geneva</hi> a multitude of Offenders took away the Scandal of the Offence, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suls Preachers and chief Citizens too, being there often punished for those very faults, which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn in others, but tho the Scandal of the Thief's evil living did at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> end with the Punishnent, yet the Thief was concern'd for fear least the report of his Crimes should reach <hi>Holland,</hi> which he took care to prevent by his dissembling with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100985:16"/>the Consistory, whose favour and good opinion he did endeavour to gain by exclaiming against his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wickedness, and did by his sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, weeping and bewailing his sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Life, so counterfeit the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that every one did pity him.</p>
            <p>After he had thus impos'd upon the Consistory, he went to do the like upon the Preacher, to whom he expresses much sorrow for the Evils which he had done; saying, <hi>that he did now detest and hate those Sins, which he had formerly acted, and that he could not now without horror and amazement think on those Sins, which were now more the subject of his Sorrow and Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, than ever they were of his Myrth and Pastimes; for that now he saw that only Shame and Confusion would be the Companions of his Life:</hi> saying also, <hi>that he did fear lest the Guilt of them, should follow him into another
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100985:17"/>World, and there condemn him to pains infinitely greater than words can express or thoughts imagine:</hi> Upon which he seems so Afflicted, that he pretends to fly the Society of Men, whom by his evil Life he had so much scandalized, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive himself of the Comforts of Life as he had of the Innocency of it; purposing now to ramble up and down like a lost Sheep, and by forrow for his Sins to make his Life as miserable as it was sinful.</p>
            <p>The Preacher thinking the Thief to be as sorrowful for his Sins as he pretended, did comfort him with the Examples of <hi>David, Solomon, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalen</hi> and others, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to write in his behalf so his Father, which he did, and so praised the Thief to his Parents, that they not only pardon him but also add forty Crowns to his former mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance which he spends as impiously as before, <hi>Reader,</hi> tho' the Character
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100985:17"/>which the Thief hath here given of of himself be sufficiently detestable, yet the remaining part is much worse: For now every place becomes the Scene of his Villanies as he confesses, saying, <hi>that in the Fields and Woods he acted the Robber, in the Towns a Cut-purse and a Thief, that he broke open Houses, and by force and deceit took away the Citizens Goods and Monies;</hi> in this kind of Life he said <hi>he lived Six Years in the Company of Knaves and Harlots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he passed through <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> without any other serious reflection but this, that all his Pleasures were to be ended in one half hour.</p>
            <p>The Preacher having heard the Thiefs Confession, only tells him <hi>that he had been a great Sinner, and that he did deserve a double hanging,</hi> asking him <hi>how he could with a laugh relate the Evils
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100985:18"/>which he had done, and whether he did not fear the loss of his Soul, nor dread to think where he must go when he did dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a Relation of Sin in the Thief ought to have occasion'd so much compassion in the Preacher as to have endeavour'd to keep the Thief from sporting at those Sins, which unrepented off, will bring him to everlasting weeping and mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning. It would have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to have told him that those Sins which had occasion'd his Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this World, would also bring him to a worse Condemnation in the next World; which would be to him, (if not prevented by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Repentance) both endless and easeless; the Preacher only chides the Thief for his unreasonable laughter, at a time, when Tears and Prayers did more become the sadness of his Condition; which (however light made on by the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100985:18"/>and himself) was indeed deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for however confident he was that he had done the <hi>Will of God</hi> in all that he did, and however confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Preacher did assert that he had <hi>lived according to God's Will.</hi> Yet I believe he will find himself miserably deceiv'd, and have when he shall be Sommon'd before the Great Tribunal, more to Answer upon the account of the impiety of his Faith than Life, which yet was so bad that I know not what could be worse, unless it was his Faith; yet neither the badness of his Life or Faith doth prevail with the Preacher any farther to consider his condition than, to ask him where he thought he should go when he did dye.</p>
            <p>To which the Thief replys, <hi>that he thought he should go to Heaven as well as the Preacher,</hi> whom he proves (from the Preachers own words) not much better than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100985:19"/>and that the Preacher might not take this supposition of the Thief for a scandal he proves his suppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Preachers Confession, who had under his own hand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd, <hi>viz. that he was blind in his understanding, that he had revolted from God, that he did daily offend God, and often with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermission violate his Laws, that his best works were meer Sins and Abominations,</hi> had this been the summ total of the Preachers Impiety, yet his Life would have been sufficiently vicious to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him as bad as the Thief. But besides, these Crimes already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, the Preacher did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg <hi>that he deserved eternal damnation, that he was prone to all Evil, and avers to all Good, with much more to the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which the Preacher is so far from denying, that without a blush
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100985:19"/>he confesseth the truth of the Thiefs Accusation, and adding impudence to his wickedness saith <hi>he did it for the Glory of God;</hi> as if it either was or could be for God's Glory to have his own Image Man, to do the Works of the Devil, as if the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty could be affronted for his Honour, or his Commands violated for his Glory. Yet this Doctrine so vile as it is, the Preacher doth assert saying, <hi>that God wills his Elect to be Sinners that they may be humble,</hi> which humility he saith doth consist in this, that we should be void of all that is good, a strange Assertion this, yet here is not in the Preachers Reply to the Thiefs Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation either the leastreflection on the Thief's Sins or excuse made for his own, but only a Confession made of as great Sins committed by himself, as he came to reprove in the Thief. The Preacher 'tis true confesseth his Sins, but signifies no Sorrow for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100985:20"/>committing them, because they were done (as he saith) <hi>for the Glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Reader</hi> according to these Men's opinions Men may honour God by offending him, become his Votaries whilst they do the works of darkness, Sin that Grace may abounds and do Evil that Good may come of it; what is this but to reverse the Gospel by turning Religion into Villany. Thus do some Men as much dishonour God by their misunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Gospel, as others do by their living a contradiction to it, which makes me think that Religion hath suffered as much by the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> as <hi>Hobbists, Atheism</hi> it self being in some measure preferable to <hi>Calvinism,</hi> the last reflecting worse upon the Divine Goodness than the first, which only attempts to throw away God's Essence, and the other his Justice; it being certainly less reproachful to deny any ones Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istence
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100985:20"/>than to load it with such frightful Crimes and Cruelties as might make one wish to be rid of it; and I appeal to any but themselves whether it be not more for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and benefit of Mankind, to have no God at all, than such an one, who is delighted in his Misery, and made him for no other end than to giorifie himself in his destruction. Such Doctrines as these tend only to advance that <hi>Atheism</hi> and <hi>Impiety</hi> which they seem to Preach down, and I am certain that the <hi>Calvinist</hi> doth as much cast away the practise of Religion as the <hi>Hobbist</hi> doth the profession of it; insine, one is impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous with Religion, the other with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. Considering how frail Man is of himself, how inclin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of his Duty, and how fond most Men are of the things of this Life, for the enjoyment of which, how willing they are to haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the loosing the Joyes of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100985:21"/>next. Now if when Men do believe all the Evil consequences of an Evil and Debaucht Life, if notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this their belief of eternal Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery becoming their everlasting Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if Men I say under these Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances dare be vicious, when their Faith obliges them to be holy; what villanies may we not expect from those Doctrines, which teach Men to believe, that God will have them to be Sinners, that they may not rely on their good Works? What is this but to encourage Men in their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness? To invite them into eternal Flames, and as it were court them to be damned.</p>
            <p>For what can so certainly exclude a Man from Heaven as his being taught that all his sinful Acts are as much the <hi>Will of God</hi> as his most pious ones.</p>
            <p>How can any Man think it neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to change his Life? who hath been already taught that he doth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100985:21"/>the <hi>Will of God,</hi> when he most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagantly defies him; this one Principle once admitted is sufficient to baffle all good Life out of the World and to make all Exortations to it useless.</p>
            <p>How is it possible to disswade Men from an ill Life? When they find it useful and advantageous for the present, and are assured by their Teachers as well as their Interests 'twill do them no harm hereafter.</p>
            <p>If (as the Preacher teacheth) we cannot be injured but by an absolute immutable and unconditional Decree, a Good Life would be not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>significant but also troublesome.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine of the Preacher makes the Thief so far from being willing to live religiously, that he declares against a Good Life, saying, <hi>that knowing the danger of a good Life, he took care to avoid it, that he might not seek justification by it, and therefore resolved without
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100985:22"/>doing any good Works to rely only on the Grace of God for Salvation:</hi> A very easie way to Heaven this, if it was but as safe, for who would ever be damn'd if a confident rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on Christ for Salvation would but obtain it, if it was as easie to go to Heaven as these Men would make it to what purpose would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or their own preachings be?</p>
            <p>The Preacher finding the Thief to draw inferences from his Doctrines, which did not consist with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to grant, because they were destructive of a good Life, chides the Thief, telling him, <hi>that he did interpret his Doctrine as if it had been the Cause of his evil Deeds,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>God forbid, and that he did only intend that Men should not seek to be justified by Works but Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Answer the Thief proves as unsatisfactory as the former, by shewing <hi>that if a Man can be saved without good Works, that then
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100985:22"/>they are useless and 'tis to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to do them.</hi> So that the Thiefs inference which the Preacher blames, is the natural result of the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers own concessions; for if good Works must be avoided that we may not rely on them, and if the omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them will do us (as many Men think) good in this Life and no harm in the next, who can we think will do violence to his inclination, or spoil his Interest, for the doing of that which will not benefit him ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this Life or the next. So that a sinful Life must needs follow from a Mans flying every thing that is good; the Thief therefore must needs infer as he did, or believe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctrines, than those which he had learn't of the Preacher, who now preaches down a good Life, with as much Zeal and Eagerness as other live it down.</p>
            <p>I shall not now enter upon the dispute whether we are justified by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100985:23"/>Faith or good Works, because they are both in and through the Merits of Christ necessary to Salvation, and if Faith hath the priority in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture because it is necessary that I should believe the Christian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before I can practise it. Yet good Works are as essentially neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary as Faith can be, because it is as much every ones duty to live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Gospel as it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; and I see no reason why Men should magnify Faith above good Works, unless it be to teach Men to believe as well as to live Religion out of the World, neither do I believe that any thing is more destructive to all true Piety, than to teach Men, that God doth out of his free Grace without any good Work of ours impute the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Christ to them whom he doth Predestinate as much as if they had perform'd themselves the obedience which Christ perform'd for them.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100985:23"/>Good God where will not the Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of some Men carry them! Here the Preacher teacheth such a Faith as is consistent with our Sins, this Faith will (according to these <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinistical</hi> Principles) bring a Man to Heaven without holiness and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him from the Regions of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, whilst he is doing the Deeds of it, this is a Faith (which if it was true) would do even more then Miracles, <hi>viz.</hi> Reconcile contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions; for it makes a Man at one and the same time a Saint and a Devil, a Faith by which a Man may believe and be damned together, a Faith by which a Man may be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Christ, whilst he doth affront him, and go to Heaven hereafter tho he lives like a Devil here.</p>
            <p>The Thief finding this Faith as agreeable to his desires, as it was to his Life, doth readily imbrace it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause by it, he could reconcile Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Sins, and believe himself
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100985:24"/>into eternal Bliss in spight of all that an evil Life can do to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>This Faith (so bad as it is) the Thief calls <hi>his pure and unspotted Faith,</hi> because it kindly gave him the hopes of Heaven and the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Vices together, and did not disturb his evil Life with any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fears of those endless Torments which did imbitter the injoyments of others who had done no more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve or fear the Divine Vengeance than the Thief, or the Preacher; so that it was not likely that he should change his Life, since he found it as agreeable to his Interest as it was to his Faith; I cannot imagine how the Preacher could so much as hope to bring the Thief to a good Life, when he had arriv'd at that height of Folly and Impudence, as to affirm it his chief Art and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest to know no Law or good Works; saying, <hi>that good Works
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100985:24"/>do make no Man good, nor evil Works make any Man bad,</hi> positively affirming <hi>that no evil Work but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fedility can damn a Man;</hi> saying, <hi>that where there is Faith, there Sin cannot burt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preacher to all these Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies of the Thief, which but to name would move a Christian to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, for they who love the holy Jesus or his Religion cannot with patience see it thus treated by not only its Professors but also Teachers, to hear such horrid Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties avoucht for Religion, and no help offorded to rescue a dying Soul from such evil Doctrines as these, shews too senseless a concern for that which next to the Salvation of our own Souls, ought to be most dear to us, <hi>viz.</hi> The Salvation of our Brethren; which these arguments of the <hi>Calvinists</hi> cannot effect, nay, their teachings are so far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting Piety, that they destroy it,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100985:25"/>for after a Man is taught that a good Life is not necessary in order to his attaining the Kingdom of Heaven, he will presently conclude it to no purpose to live well here, when it will do him no good hereafter, what can a good Life signifie to those who have been taught to place the whole of Religion upon a Faith without Works, such a Faith as this cannot serve any End of Piety, for it tends only to people Hell, and to fill the Earth with confusion, and therefore the Thief having been thus encouraged to Sin, tells the Preacher (upon his advising him to keep the Commandments if he would enter into Life) <hi>that he did admire to hear him talk so strangely, and to change his own Faith that he might perswade the Thief to change his Life, which he is so far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prevailed on to do,</hi> that he boldly tells the Preacher <hi>that he had denied the Faith by attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100985:25"/>to the Divine Laws and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments that which was due to God only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preacher not insisting on the necessity of a good Life, but crying it down that he might magnifie Faith, did thereby oblige the Thief to be vitious, whereas if the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had been really desirous of the Thiefs Salvation he should have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken'd him into a sight and sense of his Sins, by shewing him the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of a good Life, and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a wicked one; for want of teaching the Thief the necessity of a good Life, the Preacher leaves him in more wickedness than he found him.</p>
            <p>'Tis true the Preacher tells the Thief <hi>that he must abstain from sin,</hi> but why he should preach such Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to him I cannot imagine, nor assign any reason why a Man should decline doing that which is profitable and pleasant here, when it will do him no hurt hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:100985:26"/>
            <p>Thus the Thiefs evil inclinations, and the Preachers worse Principles have made him proof against all good Exhortations, insomuch that he now boldly bids defiance to a good Life and those who follow it, saying to them <hi>begon ye followers of good Works, and follow me who build my Salvation only upon the Grace and Mercy of God,</hi> saying, <hi>and that from all the Authority of</hi> Luther <hi>and</hi> Civin, <hi>that a Christian was so rich after he was baptized that he cannot knowingly and willingly lose his Salvation by any Sins how great soever they be, unless he refuse to believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preacher doth not deny ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Authority or the Doctrine, but only tells the Thief <hi>that he had freely committed many Sins, and that it was fit that he should be instructed in that will of God in which he will be obeyed by him.</hi> But what obligation any one can
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100985:26"/>have to that which is impossible I cannot understand, neither can I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that God will oblige Men to act contrary to his own Decrees con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, neither can I think of any Motive powerful enough to induce the Preacher to change his Life, and to live in obedience to those Laws which according to his own Faith he neither did nor could obey. It being impossible for him to live otherwise then he did, all his Actions being from all Eternity determin'd by an absolute immutable and unconditional Decree, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of which Doctrine did inable him to defend his impieties, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then perswade him to forsake them.</p>
            <p>When Men are by such Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as these secured in their Sins, I cannot see what less than a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle can diswade them from the Commission of those Sins which they find profitable and pleasant here,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100985:27"/>and no ways injurious to them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>For if the Profits and Pleasures of this World, do and have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd on some Men to commit Sin, who did yet believe that Sin will without Repentance damn them in another World: How much more will they do it who have been taught that their Sins will do them no harm? Had the Thief been taught to believe that those very Sins which occasion'd the loss of his Life, would also occasion the loss of his Soul: It might have done him good, but alass! the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Thief is by his ill imbib'd opinions enabled to baffle whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can be said to him concerning a holy Life, which he most effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally doth, by asserting a twofold <hi>Will in God,</hi> one of which he calls <hi>Gods occult Will,</hi> the other <hi>his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd Will,</hi> saying, <hi>that God by his occult Will intends many things
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100985:27"/>should be done, which he declared he would not have done; and this he endeavours to prove by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of</hi> Pharaoh, saying, <hi>that God did by</hi> Moses <hi>declare accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his reveal'd Will, he would have.</hi> Pharaoh <hi>let the Children of</hi> Israel <hi>go, tho' by his occult Will he would not have him let them go,</hi> most blasphemously affirming, <hi>that God hath by his hidden Will appointed those to commit Sin, whom by his reveal'd Will he hath commanded to live well:</hi> This im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Notion of the Thief had arm'd him against whatever might be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise useful to bring him from his wicked course of Life, which was like to do him more harm in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World, than it had or could do in this.</p>
            <p>The Preacher having admitted these two contrary Wills in God, finds himself unable to resist the force of the Thiefs arguments for
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100985:28"/>a wicked Life, there being no way to secure a good Life, but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying these two contrary Wills in God. The Preacher not taking this Method, found all his Arts and Arguments useless to perswade the Thief to a good Life, for if the Preacher offers never so many Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives from holy Scripture, the Thief is by this distinction enabled to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Crimes with as much ease as he did commit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and doth thereby render the Preachers next question ineffectual; it being indeed to no purpose to ask the Thief whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he thought he did <hi>the Will of God</hi> by sinning, which tho' rhe Preacher had formerly granted, yet now finding the mischievousness of his Grant, was willing to recall it, but the Thief finding the useful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of this distinction, answers the Preachers question with as much ease as he did propose it, saying, <hi>that if the Preacher did by</hi> the Will of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100985:28"/>God <hi>understand his reveal'd Will that then by sinning he did not do</hi> the Will of God, <hi>but if by</hi> the Will of God <hi>he meant</hi> Gods hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Will, he saith, <hi>that then by sinning he did</hi> the Will of God.</p>
            <p>Thus the Thief did distinguish himself out of his Religion and Happiness, and is by the help of this distinction become proof against all Arguments which can be brought for his Conversion; and therefore it was to no purpose in the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (after he had admitted these two <hi>Wills in God</hi>) to tell the Thief that he ought to have regarded to <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd Will of God,</hi> for why should he have regard to <hi>the reveal'd Will of God,</hi> who did believe that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever God did command by his <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd Will,</hi> he design'd the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by his hidden <hi>Will,</hi> by which he did often, if not always make voy'd his <hi>reveal'd Will.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:100985:29"/>
            <p>This Faith which the Thief had learnt of the Preacher, makes him hug and applaud himself in his Vices, triumphing over the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers insignificant Discourse, and challenging him to answer the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments which his Faith had taught him to make against a good Life, insomuch that he boldly argues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a good Life, saying, <hi>if I am reprobated, all the care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence which I can use will do me no good, yea tho' I do the good Works of all the Saints I could not be saved; but if I am Predestina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Sin can do me no harm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause neither my Sins nor the Sins of the whole World are able to defeat omnipotence, or revers the Decrees of Heaven, or change that which is immutable and unconditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, for if it be immutable, how can it be changed, and if it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conditional then a good Life can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> (saith the Thief) <hi>be the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100985:29"/>of my entring into bliss, and of enjoying those pleasures which are above.</hi> To this Discourse of the Thief the Preacher offers no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer because he knew the Thiefs Arguments were agreeable to his Faith, altho' they did not only not favour a good Life, but were also inconsistent with it, yet the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er doth not reprehend the Thief for his impious Opinions, but lets him go on in his Sins, without endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to wake him out of that Lithargy into which his Sins had cast him. The Preacher finding it was impossible to change the Thiefs Life, without first changing his Faith, doth no longer perswade him to a good Life, but only asks him whether he did never hear God calling him to Repentance and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Life.</p>
            <p>To which the Thief answer'd, <hi>that he had heard God calling him eternally, but that he could not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100985:30"/>obey him, because God did by his internal Call Predestinate him to disobey his external Call,</hi> saying, <hi>that God's calling externally, did signifie little, unless he had inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally called and Predestinated him to do what he was pleased to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> for saith the Thief <hi>it p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from God's eternal Decrees, that be gives Faith to some and denies it to others, and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Decree, God doth gratiously soften the hearts of his Elect, whilst he leaves others to their own Obdurateness and Malice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> were these things indeed so as the Thief had represented them, a good Life would then be both needless and insignificant, for that according to this Doctrine, tho' God call never so often yet this will do him no good, because of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Decree made to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for saith the Thief, <hi>that tho'
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100985:30"/>some are converted by the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Gospel,</hi> yet this saith he, <hi>is not to be ascribed to Man's free Will, but to God, who hath from all eternity chosen in Christ those who are his, without any regard to their good Works,</hi> were this true, what can a good Life sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie?</p>
            <p>Tho' this Doctrine be false, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, and irrational, yet the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er doth not so much as reprehend the Thief for the Blasphemies which he uttered; but instead of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to prevent the Ruin of a dying Soul, he now seems to oblige him to despair, because he could not keep him from presuming, or else he would not have asked him whether he did not think himself a Reprobate.</p>
            <p>To which the Thief answers (tho' without any concern for his present or future Interest) <hi>that he thought himself reprobated, and that not<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100985:31"/>without cause,</hi> for saith he, <hi>God hath Reprobated the greatest Part of Mankind out of his mere good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, that by their death he might glorifie his great Name.</hi> Good God! that Men should arrive at so great a height of Impiety and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, as to believe that God would from all Eternity without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his Actions create Man to damn him. Is it possible to believe that God who had declared himself to be gratious and merciful, slow to anger, and of great pitty, that he should not only say, but also swear, <hi>that he did not desire the death of a sinner,</hi> that I say he should not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding his Word, and his Oath, everlastingly torment his own Image Man: Is so impiously vile, but to conceive, that it is enough to make a Man not only forfeit his Christianity but also his Humanity too, for certainly to believe and assert such Blasphemies as these of our good
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100985:31"/>God, is proper only to Devils, and to those who count Religion a cheat, and the Gospel it self a Fable; for surely none but such could talk so dishonourably of God as to make God's Glory the Cause not only of Men's Misery, but also of their Sins.</p>
            <p>What is this but to lible God and Religion? to affirm that he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishes us for those faults which he Decree'd us to commit, forcing us to Sin, that he might destroy us for the doing that which by his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees he oblig'd us to.</p>
            <p>This Calumny is so false and vile, that if it were true, I know not what would be said worse of the Devil himself; yet this Doctrine so vile as it is, is so far from being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Preacher, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives it as well as the Thief, and impiously affirms that God hath from all Eternity, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Sin, by his pure absolute Decree, rejected the greatest part of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100985:32"/>Mankind, and created them for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, saying that if any Man doth affirm that God hates no Man as he is Man, and made him, he contradicts the Apostle.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine is so injurious to God so vile in its self and so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable to Mankind, that I wonder it was not cast out of the World with as much horror as it was with shame brought into it, and however these Doctrines come to be part of the <hi>Calvinists</hi> Creed, yet I must confess I think them so vile that I admire any should be so wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as to teach it, or believe them.</p>
            <p>Those Doctrines being in my judgment unfit to be believed of God, which are a scandal to Man; for let a Man be never so just as to one Will, when he is unjust to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the innocency of one Will can never excuse the injustice of the other, and I cannot conceive how those Doctrines can be thought an
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100985:32"/>honour to God, which are a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to Man, and I am inclin'd to believe that however confident the <hi>Calvinists</hi> are to teach these Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, yet their Hearers should fear to believe them: For it seems strange to me that the Notion which Men generally have of Justice in this World, should not make them fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to say those things of God which they would think reproachful to be said of themselves, and I find the Thief in spight of his Faith, (which did so much favour him in his Sins) begin to despond of his Salvation; for upon the Preachers asking him if he did not think himself a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate he presently confest his fears, which he could not easily be rid of; for notwithstanding the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er advised him not to Despair, yet he becomes sad and melancholy, and to fear least a Life so shameful as his, should meet with with an End as Tragical as Dismal, so that he now
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100985:33"/>despairs of attaining that Happiness which not long since he expected to enjoy, and asks <hi>how it is possible for one whose Life hath been so shameful as his not to despond of injoying that goodness which he had so often offronted no less by his Faith than Life, especially since he found Infants as well as the Aged are condemned before they have done Good or Evil: And therefore he infers that when In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are thus treated by Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God before they have done Good or Evil, and consider that they are not only the Children of</hi> Turks <hi>and</hi> Heathens, <hi>but also the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Infants of believing Parents who are thus used, he thinks it reasonable to fear least those Sins for which he was condemn'd to lose his Life, might also occasion him to loose his Soul.</hi> In such doleful Circumstances as these the Preacher doth not endeavour to bring the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100985:33"/>Thief from his disponding thoughts of his Reprobation, nor from his evil Sentiments of Gods severity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Infants, neither doth he offer one word in reproof of either, which makes the Thief's Case very deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to meet with a Guide who in his last Agonies is so far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to help and assist him that instead of rescuing him by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations and Councils from his sad condition, he doth as it were assign him to the Sufferings of all those Miseries which he pretends in so much kindness to free him from, which makes me think, that as that Man's Life is to be despaired of, whose Physician is so far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to Cure his Distemper, that all his Applications if relyed on will certainly destroy him, so may his Soul be justly despired of, whose Guide is so far from healing his Soul's Disease, that he encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth all its Maladies, and will
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100985:34"/>if he doth not find it sick, make it so.</p>
            <p>This seems to me to be the poor Thief's Case, who is now like to suffer more by the ill conduct of the Preacher, than by the Sentence of the Judge, or by the Execution of the Hangman. His Chains are not so disgraceful to him as the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Doctrine is dangerous, for the disgrace of his Chains will end with his natural Life, but the other will last as long as Eternity its self shall endure: The Haugman did by his Office deliver the Thief from the trouble and shame of a miserable Life, but the Preacher doth either through the ignorance of his Office or his willful perverting of it, as it were assign him over to all the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Torments of another World; where I am affraid he will suffer more upon the account of his Faith than Life, and tho' I confess he hath reason to bewail his unhappy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100985:34"/>in meeting with Companions to draw him to Sin, yet he will have much more reason to bewail him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self that he unhappily met with such a Guide, who taught him to believe, worse than he had lived, for the vitiousness of his Life was only to be exceeded by the greater Impiety of his Frith.</p>
            <p>The Preacher he finding the Thief unwilling to change his Life, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to confirm him in the Belief of his own Reprobation. And this he doth by an Argument drawn from Mens being by the Almighty permitted to kill an Ox or a Sheep for their use, or to hunt a Hare for their pleasure, from which he infers that if a Man can justly do this to inferiour Creatures for his pleasure, that then the great God may much more justly reject for his Glory his Creatures, saying, <hi>that it is a thousand times more just that all the Creatures in Heaven and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100985:35"/>Earth should serve by their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death, for the demonstration of the Glory of God's Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty; than that the killing of a fly or a knit should serve for the demonstration of the Honour of all the Men in the World:</hi> And this he doth most extravagently affirm ought to be so far from being disliked in God, that the Elect ought to give thanks that God hath reprobated the Wicked, that he might evidence how much he loved his Elect, and what is more strange he confidently saith, <hi>that the wicked themselves ought not to complain that they are reprobated, but rather to give God thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where will not the Impiety of Men lead them, and what will they fear to say or do when they dare thus believe? What can we expect from such a Faith as this, which is so far from teaching Men to be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it is a shame not only to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100985:35"/>religious, but even to an honest Man to own it: It being at once both Impious and Irrational, because it makes Men talk against Heaven and their own Interest.</p>
            <p>It is certainly a great Sin to think dishonourably of God, but surely it is much worse to blaspheme him, we ought to adore by speaking more vilely of him than we dare do one of another. I am perswaded that such bold Impieties as these, will not long pass unpunished, for God will not always suffer himself to be affronted by Dust and Ashes, and certainly a greater affront cannot be offered to the Almighty than to think any Man so much to be hated by him as to damn him only for his pleasure, who had not first provok't him by a wicked and impenitent Life; no certainly, our gratious God only makes them the Subjects of his eternal Fury, who have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd his Favours, and they only
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100985:36"/>feel his Wrath, who would not except of his Mercy unless they might injoy that and their Sins together.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding the Preacher boldly affirms, <hi>that it is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand times more just, that all the Creatures in Heaven and Earth should only for God's pleasure serve his Glory by their death. Tho' they had not offended him, than that the death of a Knit or a F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y should serve for the honour or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of all the Men in the World.</hi> I cannot but dissent from him for these two Reasons.</p>
            <p n="1">1st. Because there is no Parallel between our destroying Creatures inferiour to our selves, when they are of another Species; and are not able to make Pacts and Covenants with us, we being not obliged by any Oaths or Promises to them, may without doing them any wrong,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100985:36"/>make use of that Power which God hath given us over them; but</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The case is different in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the time of using our Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over them, the pain being but short that we put them to; either in our killing them for our use, or hunting them for our pleasure, so that tho' our gratious God might (as he is absolute Lord of all Men and things) have treated us as he did please. Yet since he hath by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises encouraged us to serve him, he will reward those Services which himself hath enjoyn'd, and which we have undergone for the sake of Christ and the Gospel: So that whatever fears we may have upon the account of God's being Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord, yet they will soon va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish when we consider the many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises which he hath made to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage our obedience, especially when
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100985:37"/>all his other Attributes do speak as much Goodness to us, as his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence doth power over us; we may with as much comfort expect the performance of his Promise if we do well, as fear his Anger when we do Evil, by which it is manifest that a Power limited by Promises and Conditions is vastly different from a free Power; and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is as great in respect of the time as it is in respect of the Agent. For tho' a Man may kill an Ox or a Sheep for his use, yet surely he could not unprovok'd only to shew his Power give the Ox or Sheep an Eternal Being for no other purpose then to give them an eternal Mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I cannot think any thing called Man could be so inhumane; for whosoever can be so cruel, he must have put off Humanity on this side and Hell, commenced Devil, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order to be used like one hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:100985:37"/>
            <p>That can never be for the honour of God which is a disgrace to Man. It is impossible that God should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light himself in the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of his Creatures, or be pleas'd with the everlasting Sighs and Tears of those whom he did once so much love and honour as to create them in his Image, and Redeem them with the Blood of his Son, it is I say incredible that after such kindness expressed towards Man, God should Predestinate him to be wicked and then damn him for being so, to do this would be so wicked and unjust, so contrary to his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and so uncomfortable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that I know not which to wonder at most, whether there should be Men vile enough to teach these Doctrines, or that any should be such Fools as to believe them upon their being taught, both of them seeming to me equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:100985:38"/>
            <p>The Preacher seems not only to believe this Doctrine of God's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probating for his good pleasure whom he pleases, but also is become so extravagant as to assert that the Reprobate themselves ought not to complain of it, but rather to give God thanks, that by their Death they can glorifie his holy Name.</p>
            <p>To this and much more spoken by the Preacher to the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, the Thief not daring to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Doctrine which he had been taught by the Preacher. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers to the Preachers Assertion, by a distinction, saying, <hi>that if a Man did only respect his own private Good, he had then cause to complain of the severity of those Decrees by which he was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to everlasting Flames, and this be thinks reasonable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, because it would be against the Nature of Mankind to give thanks for Troubles and Afflictions,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100985:38"/>and to take eternal Torments for a Favour, or Damnation for a Blessing.</hi> These certainly would sit too uneasie and heavy on those who suffered them; to make them so far mistake their Interest as to take them for Obligations; no certainly on the contrary, his perpetual Torments would make him with horror remember the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of his Misery, rather than to move him to be thankful for the kindness of never dying Calamities. Man who was thus treated would certainly make perpetual imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons against the Author of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery, rather than thank him that he was so far pleased to consult his Glory, as to make his Misery to be endless, that his Glory might be so too; and therefore I cannot but imagine that tho' the Thief doth acknowledge that for a publick good it is best for a Man to be damned; yet this Doctrine is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:100985:39"/>contradicted by the reason of Mankind, as well as by the woeful experience of those who are obliged to suffer any great Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; and however, this Doctrine is not contradicted by the Preacher, who doth not reprove the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonableness of it, but only tells the Thief <hi>that it was better for him to spend his time in being obedient to God's Word, than in the vindication of the</hi> Doctrine of Reprobation, <hi>which he thought he had firmly fixed in his mind to the great neglect of the Practice of those Duties which through his Repentance and Faith in Christ might have prevented that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation which he did now fear would shortly become his portion</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Preacher forgets his former Assertions, wherein he had made obedience to God's Laws, and Preaching so far from being
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100985:39"/>to all people beneficial, that he makes it do much harm to those who are Reprobated, saying, <hi>that to them it proves a Snare, and an occasion of their greater Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> And (according to the Preacher) it is made thus fatal to them, not for any fault commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them to deserve to be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of God's Fury, but upon the account of his Decrees made for that purpose.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine is so rediculous that a reasonable Man would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther think it did deserve or need a Confutation.</p>
            <p>After such Preachments as these I do not understand of what use Religion can be, when Men have been taught that those Ordinances of God, which are to the Elect the ways and means of Salvation; do to those who are reprobated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Snares, and the means of their Condemnation, this makes the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100985:40"/>Thief boldly affirm, <hi>that they who are Reprobated, cannot obey God, believe, nor be justified or saved, and that because God will not convert them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If against this Blasphemy of the Thief it be objected that God doth frequently make offers of his Grace to all, and so consequently to the Reprobate; to this the Thief saith, <hi>that God doth offer his Gract to the Reprobate themselves, tho' not with an intent to benefit and save them but with a design to make them the more unexcusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he may punish them the more grievously;</hi> what is this but to make God as very a Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite as themselves?</p>
            <p>To this Doctrine, so vile as it is, the Preacher readily assents, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that God did call some Men to an ill Life, in order to make them the Subjects of his Anger, and the Examples of his Fury,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100985:40"/>which that they may be,</hi> the Preacher saith, <hi>that God deprives them of the Power of hearing his Word to their advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Answer of the Preacher is so full of discouragement to a good Life, that I cannot imagine what more powerful Argument the Preacher could make use of to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Thief in a ill Life, then thus to run down a good one.</p>
            <p>This makes me think that as some Seeds will not grow in some Grounds, that so a good Life can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be attain'd by such Doctrines as have been taught by the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and believed by the Thief. Doctrines which carry on the work of Darkness as effectually as if an Emissary of Darkness had been sent from thence to teach it, Sathan and all his Agents being unable to blaspheme God, and Religion more than the Thief, and Preacher have done.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:100985:41"/>
            <p>'Tis certainly a very prepostrous way of endeavouring to bring a Man from an evil Life, by decry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Benefits of a good One, for can any Man so much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or hope to bring that Man to a good Life; who hath been already taught that it may prove a Snare to him, and occasion his deeper Damnation.</p>
            <p>Alass! Such Doctrines as these which make preaching useless, must necessarily make a good Life so too, for why should any one desire to lead a good Life, when it may become a Snare to him when he believes it not only useless, but also injurious to him If such Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as these be not invitations and encouragements to an evil Life, I know not what is or can be. I am sure the Thief made this use of them, and did therefore fly all Sermons, Exhortations and good Works. I he Preacher being
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:100985:41"/>as ready to approve of the Thiefs Blasphemy, as the other to utter it; lets him now injoy that Faith, by which he might live like a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and yet injoy Heaven.</p>
            <p>For this is a Faith by which a Man may justifie his Sins to God's Face, as well as commit them in his Presence; for when he shall be brought before the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Tribunal, and be ask'd why he did not live according to God's Commandments, he may (according to these Men's Principles) reply, <hi>I have lived as I have been taught by my Pastors and Parents, and I thought these were more wise to choose a Religion for me than I was for my self; I have as much done your Will as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creature, and I do hope because I have lived according my Faith, that I may be of the number of those happy Ones, who may glorifie your Holy Name by
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:100985:42"/>my Salvation, and that you will not mignifie your self in my destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I have I confess lived in those Sins to which according to your reveal'd Will you have threatned everlasting Torments, and according to which I can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing but your Anger and Indignation; but yet since by your secret will you did determine I should violate your reveal'd Will, I hope that my complyance with the latter will excuse my violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the former, I did not it is ture pray, read Sermons, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacraments, because tho' I found to have done these Duties would have been profitable to me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your reveal'd Will, yet believing that according to your secret Will it would be dangerous and destructive to have done them, I thought I should do more for my own Safety, as well as your Glory, wholly to avoid all good
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100985:42"/>Works, and to rely only on your Mercy for my Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Men are once satisfied with such a Faith as this, I do not see how they can be prevaild on to lead holy Lives, for if the <hi>Calvinistical</hi> Notions concerning the Divine Decrees were indeed true, a good Life would be use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less and insignificant, and what is worse troublesome too, so that this belief doth as it were give Men up to a vicious Life here, against which Life there are so many threats in holy Scripture, that I am inclin'd to believe that those who boast most of their Predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; do yet sometimes admit of desponding thoughts about their Salvation.</p>
            <p>For however, bold some Men are in setting up two different Wills in God, as contrary to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as his Laws are to their Lives, and however secure they seem to be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100985:43"/>in their vain hopes of being Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinated to eternal Life while they are doing the Deeds of Darkness, yet the reveal'd Will of God speaks too many bitter things against them to be comforted by his hidden Will, which he now makes use of, that he may excuse his violation of God's reveal'd Will; yet his considence of his Salvation will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his being doom'd to eternal Destruction, for the truth of God is not varied according to the senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men, and the Thief and those of his perswasion will find I believe that a bold presumption of Mercy is no sign of Election, nor an ill Life any qualification for Heaven; and tho' the Thief, as the Preacher tells him, had shewn no fruites of his Election, so I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve however confident he now is, yet when summon'd before the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Tribunal he will have no hopes of his Salvarion, and tho' the Thief
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:100985:43"/>is now so confident as to think that notwithstanding his ill Life, it was yet more manifest than the Sun at noon day, that he ought not to despair, yet his confidence will then vanish, and he too late find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self miserably deceived, in believing that his Salvation was founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Election.</p>
            <p>The Thief having by these Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines learnt to reconcile Heaven to his Sins, and the Deeds of Darkness to the Rewards of the Children of Light, is resolved not to make his Life dismal by Repentance, tho' he had made his Death dishonourable by his Crimes.</p>
            <p>Thus according to <hi>Calvinistical</hi> Principles nothing is necessary to Salvation but a strong opinion of our Election, and Adoption in Christ Jesus.</p>
            <p>That those who are Elected and Adopted by the holy Jesus shall be
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100985:44"/>saved, I do most firmly believe, but I cannot think any Man either Elected or Adopted by him who neglecting to live a good Lifs is so confident as to think that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the vain supposition of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Predestinated that an evil Life will not Damn him, for surely if we are by Nature the Children of Wrath, we are much more so by Sin, being by the Commission of it become Enemies to God we have more reason to dread his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, than expect his Favour, and to fear least an imaginary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree should not be able to keep the Wrath of God from falling on us.</p>
            <p>The rest of the Preachers and Thiefs discourse being as blasphemous and as useless as what he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready said. I shall no farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider it, than as it shall serve to assert my last Engagement, <hi>viz.</hi> To give such an account of the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100985:44"/>Divine Decrees as may through God's Grace prevent others from falling into the like horrid Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which the Thief had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed, and this I shall endeavour to do.</p>
            <p>First by shewing that an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, immutable and unconditional Decree is inconsistent with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodness. And</p>
            <p>Secondly, by shewing that such a Decree would make Religion use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less.</p>
            <p n="1">1st. An absolute immutable and unconditional Decree is inconsistent with the Divine Goodness.</p>
            <p>That God's Goodness is equal to his other Perfections, is a truth so Universally acknowledged, that it needs no proof. Now how an infinite Goodness can be delighted with the destruction of the Work of his own hands, or glory in the everlasting Weeping and Mourning
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100985:45"/>of those to whom he was once so kind, as to redeem them with the blood of his Son, from all the Evils which they were subjected to by <hi>Adam's</hi> Fall, that he should by so inestimable a price as the blood of his Son, purchase our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that he should afterward without any provocation assign us to eternal Misery, is so improbable and so unjust an imputation to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodness, that I know not what can be said worse of the vilest of Men, or of the Devil himself.</p>
            <p>The doing this may speak him Omnipotent indeed, thus to raise to himself Trophies from the ruin of his People, but surely such an Omnipotence, without Goodness, would be a little for God's Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as for Man's Comfort, and so consequently not to be believed of God, who hath oblig'd himself by promise to Reward with eternal
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:100985:45"/>Life all those who Fight manfully under his Banners, against Sin, the World and Devil, and it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that he will perform what he hath promised, and will not disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Hopes of his People, nor doom them to never dying Sighs and Groans, for no other intent then to glorifie his Name in their destruction, for to do this would be contrary to his Word, his Promise and his Oath, and must therefore be inconsistent with his Goodness, and not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; because it is neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable nor reasonable that God should make such difference between his own Creatures upon no other Motive then his own Will, to do this would be unjust in a Man, and therefore not to be attributed to the Great God.</p>
            <p>For who would not think it to be at once both dishonourable and unjust in a Man to be always
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:100985:46"/>beating and tormenting some of those under his Command, only to shew his Power over them, or what is as bad that he might endear himself to his Favorites, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding his kindness to them, did as little deserve his love as those whom he made the miserable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his endless Fury: For it cannot excuse the partiallity of his Actings towards them; to pretend that their disobedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands had occasion'd his Wrath against them, when himself at the same time had Predestinated them not to obey him.</p>
            <p>However confident these Men talk of the righteous Judge of all the Earth, yet to do this would be so vile, that as bad as the World is, I cannot think any Man (were it in his power) bad enow to do it, and therefore do deem it dishonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God to impute those Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties to him, which the most Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yious
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:100985:46"/>would abhor, and even Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it self startle and recoil at. For such Acts as these are suitable to those Natures only who being doomed to eternal Misery them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, do endeavour to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Torments as lasting as their own; for tho' in Hell it may be some ease to the pains of the damned, or at least some satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to their Malice perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to torment each other, yet to affirm this of God or Man, would be dishonourable to both, especially to God, and as to Man, who would ever affirm that Person to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an honest or a good Man, who should send his Servant to the Gallies, and there make him a Slave for Life, and that for no other reason then because he did not at his Masters command ride such or such a Journey, when at the same time his Master had chain'd him so fast that he might as well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:100985:47"/>the Earth as to go beyond the length of his Chain, neither would it make the Master a jot the honester Man, tho' he had at the same time encourag'd him by all the fair promises imaginable, nay, tho' he had sworn to him that he did not desire to send him to the Gailies, but that he had much rather that he would go his Journey, perform his Commands, and be happy in his Favour, if after all these Invitations to a holy Life, he had made it impossible for him to obey, all these preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Masters Innocence, Pitty or kindness, would only serve to make his Master the greater tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing Hypocrite; and I appeal to the Sentiments of Mankind, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther such proceedings in the Master, would not be thought much more reprovable than the imaginary fault which he threatned to punish so severely in the Servant, nay, it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:100985:47"/>would be inconsistent with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Justice and Goodness thus to punish faults of his own making, which laads me to another reason; why an absolute immutable and unconditional Decree is not to be admitted. And that is</p>
            <p>Secondly because such a Decree would make Religion useless.</p>
            <p>Altho' this hath been in a great measure proved in the foregoing pages, yet I shall further shew it, by replying to some Objections which many of the <hi>Calvinisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Party do Glory and Triumph in, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That all Men do so much dread the Wrath of God, and are so afraid to be damned, that these absolute Decrees are not so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to Piety, as those who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oppose them, would make the World believe, because (say they) <hi>many who teach this Doctrine are
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:100985:48"/>Men of the best lives and most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Conversations</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Objection, (if it be not rather a Compliment to their Party than a Truth) I Answer, that those of them who thus live, do not lead their Lives according to their Faith, which makes their Salvation to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon their Election, which they hold to be absolute, now if those only shall be saved who are thus Elected, then a good Life is useless; for unless it can reverse the Decree of Heaven, and change the Sentence of Death into the Rewards of eternal Life, it cannot be useful, and if it can, how is the Decree im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable? And if a good Life be in no sense neither the Cause nor the Condition of Man's Salvation, it is altogether useless; and if it be in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny sense advantageous to our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it then destroys this Doctrine of the Decrees; so that whosoever of them is exemplary for his Piety,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:100985:48"/>he owes (I am confident) his Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more to his Fears than Faith, as to the other part of their Objection, that those who believe this Doctrine are generally Men of the best lives, I must needs say I look upon it to be false, and did I think it as necessary to expose their Lives as Faith, it would be easie to prove their Lives not much better than their Faith. but</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They Object <hi>that God may as he is Sovereign Lord of all the World, dispose of Man as well as of all other Creatures, and Things in it, as he pleaseth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Answer, that tho' as absolute Lord, God might dispose of us as he pleases; yet since he is Just and Good as well as Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and hath by promises obliged himself to Reward us if we do well, we have more reason to hope in his Mercy, and to love him for his
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:100985:49"/>Goodness than whilst we do well, to dread him for his Omnipotence, or to believe or argue our selves out of our Happiness upon the account of his Power; for tho' as he is Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent he can do what he pleases, yet he hath a Will to do only that which is Just, so that his Power thus sweetned by his Goodness, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a support, and not a terror to his People, and therefore cannot tend to the Destruction of those Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which himself hath made. God will not unprovok't, deprive any of his Creatures of that Happiness which he purchased for them by the blood of his Son. How is it possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any Man to think that God will destroy those Souls which he sent his Son to to save; which will lead me to another Objection, which I take to be the most material that ever I heard offered in Vindication of their Decrees, and that is taken from the 9th Chapter of the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:100985:49"/>and the 11th 12th and 13th verse, <hi>for the Children</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>being not yet born, neither having done any Good or Evil, that the purpose of God according to Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might stand, not of Works, but of him that calleth, it was said unto her, the elder shall serve the younger, as it is written,</hi> Jacob <hi>have I loved, but</hi> Esau <hi>have I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> From these texts the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> thus argue, That if before Men were born, and before they had done Good or Evil, God did hate one and love the other; and that upon no other account but that his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose according to his Election might stand as he affirms, saying, Jacob <hi>have I loved, but</hi> Esau <hi>have I hated,</hi> then say they, <hi>it is plain that God's Election is the Cause of Man's Salvation and not good Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Answer, that tho' God's Goodness be the efficient Cause of Man's Salvation; yet his
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:100985:50"/>living <hi>according to God's Will</hi> was the condition of his Election, and that tho' when God was pleased to make his Election concerning them, they had not then done either Good or Evil, yet God by his prescience knowing what they would do, Elects them through the Merits of his Son for what in time they should do, so that God's Decrees are not uncondi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, for tho' as to the Cause of our Election, God hath no regard to our Works, yet he hath as to the condition of them, and whereas they Object <hi>that God loved</hi> Jacob, <hi>but hated</hi> Esau.</p>
            <p>To this part of the Objection I Answer, that the Word <hi>Hatred</hi> is not in this Text, to be taken in the strickest Sense as it signifies any Act of ill will to <hi>Esau,</hi> more than to <hi>Jacob,</hi> but in a milder Sense as it signifies only a less love, and in this Sense the Word <hi>Hate,</hi> is taken in the 14th Chapter of the Gospel accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to St. <hi>Luke,</hi> and the 26th
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:100985:50"/>Verse, where our Saviour speaking of himself saith, <hi>If any Man come to me and hates not his Father and Mother, Wife and Children, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Sisters, yea, and his own Life also, he cannot be my Disciple.</hi> Now it is manifest that our blessed Saviour would never oblige us to love our Enemies, and hate our Parents, for this was to reverse Nature; God is so far from requiring us in this Sense to hate them, that he hath injoyn'd us to Honour and Obey them, and promised us a Reward for our doing it, and also threatned to punish our disobedience to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, it would be unnatural to hate the Authors of our Being, and to wish Evil to those, whom Nature as well as Kindness had made obliging to us; And therefore to hate can in this place signifie no more than a less love, in which Sense it becomes reasonable, because we are in Duty as well as Gratitude obliged to love every Creature and Thing less than
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:100985:51"/>God; for tho' we may have many obligations to our Friends and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, yet we have more to engage us to the Love and Service of our God, who is daily doing us good: So that whether we consider his Power over us, or love to us, we ought to love him above all things, and this is all we are obliged too; for to understand the Word <hi>Hate</hi> in the former Sense, would be against the Law of Nature, and make us to become Barbarous and Salvage, that we may be Religious; as if it was our duty to become Bruits in this World, that we may be Saints in the next: And this shall lead me to the next thing proposed, <hi>viz.</hi> To prove that the Doctrine of an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute immutable and unconditional Decree, would make all Religion useless, and that for these two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Because it deprives us of those Powers which are necessary to our living well.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:100985:51"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Because this Doctrine makes all endeavours useless.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To what purpose is it for a Man to attempt the doing of that which he had neither Will, Means, nor Power to perform, for let a Man be never so well inclin'd in himself to practice Vertue, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive never so good Exhortations to the doing it, yet this Absolute and Unconditional Decree would render all his good Thoughts and Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions useless, and make the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of others as vain as his own endeavours, for tho' what God Commands by his <hi>Reveal'd Will,</hi> doth not only seem, but also is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, rational, and advantageous; yet God having made it by his hidden Will impossible to be done, it must needs be idle to attempt it.</p>
            <p>For the impossibility of the Act may justly discourage the Agent from the doing that which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves impossible; and so far should I be from hoping to perswade any
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:100985:52"/>Man to do that which both he and I did think impossible that I should not deem it either prudence or good manners to attempt it, and I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that according to these Men's Principles I do not see how any Man can Answer this common Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, <hi>viz. That if I am Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinated to eternal Life I shall be saved, whatever I do, or however I live: If I am not, all my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours will be useless and insignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</hi> For that Men's Acts cannot change the Laws of Heaven, and this is so evident in its self, that if I did not design brevity, I could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplyfie it in every Instance of the Christian Religion; but I shall at present only Instance in the two great Duties of Prayer and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First of Prayer,</hi> Should a <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistical</hi> Preacher go to one of his own Congregation who was sick, and desire him to pray, I cannot imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne how he could so much as
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:100985:52"/>hope to prevail, I should rather think that his Conscience would fly in his Face for attempting to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade another to do that which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self did deem impossible, for suppose a <hi>Calvinist</hi> should come to a Sinner on his Death-bed, and exhort him to pray for the pardon of the Sins which he had committed: How ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily might he reply, <hi>Alass Sir! what you exhort me to, is not in my power to perform, and I cannot but admire that you exhort me in a dying hour to act contrary to the Faith you have taught me; which makes not only my Prayers, but also your Preaching vain, nay, you your self must change your Faith, or else believe as I do; for you have told me, that I am Predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from all Eternity to do all that I shall at any time be able to perform, so that if I am Predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to pray, I shall pray whether you exhort me to it or not, and if I am not Predestinated to it, your
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:100985:53"/>Exhortations will do me no good, because they cannot change an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Decree. For if I am deereed to be Damn'd, than neither you nor I can any more pray me into Heavon than you could pray me out of Hell. If I was now tormented in those Hames, to what purpose is it then to pray? since my Prayers cannot Reverse my doom for if it could the Decree would not be Immutable, and if it cannot, Prayer is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly useless, but also troublesome, and betomes rather an Argument of Folly, than Duty to set about that which a Man hath no Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers to perform; so that however reasonable Prayer may be to those who expect advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages from it, yet it cannot be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued by him, who be lieves it will do him no good.</hi> Thus Reader you may see how useless this Impious Doctrine doth render this excellent Duty of Prayer. And so likewise it doth.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:100985:53"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, The great Duty of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> For let the Preacher press his Arguments with all imaginable Rhetorick, and with all the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Motives and Advantages that words can express or thought ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, yet the belief of these <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistical</hi> Decrees will so discourage his hopes, as that he will not attempt the doing that, which if it was not for these Decrees would appear both irreligious and irrational not to have done.</p>
            <p>Repentance is in it self so reaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and so really advantageous, that where there is any probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its being successful for the end it is design'd, it then carries its own Invitations and Rewards with it; yet when a Man meets with one whose Religion teaches him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that neither Repentance nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Act can do him good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God by his Decrees had made him only to damn him: When Men have espoused such Doctrines as these,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:100985:54"/>I do not see how such an one can be brought from an ill Life, without first bringing him from a worse Faith. For if the <hi>Calvinist</hi> represents to him the sadness of his Condition, and from thence draws Motives to perswade him to amend his Life, how easily may be silence this and whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever else could be said, by saying, <hi>he was Predestinated to do all that he did, and could not do otherwise.</hi> But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Because This Doctrine makes all endeavours useless.</p>
            <p>To enjoy the Kingdom of Heaven is so desirable an attainment, that no pains and labours how great so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can be thought to much to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chace it. The excellency of the Prize will highly recompence all our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and no reason can be assign'd why Men should not endeavour to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, unless it be this Doctrine of the <hi>Calvinistical</hi> Decrees. For 'tis to no purpose to endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade one to attempt an impossibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:100985:54"/>tho' it was most useful and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable both for his present and future Interest, for could all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments imaginable drawn from the most prevailing Motives, perswade a Man to undertake to make an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine as intelligent as a Man, or a Child of two days old as learn'd as <hi>Origin.</hi> Now tho' the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves are sufficiently inviting to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the doing of it, yet the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility of it would make it ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to attempt it: And so it is in relation to Religion, and I have no more reason to perswade one to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt an impossibility in relation to Religion, than in relation to any other thing, it being impractical and rude to offer to perswade any Man to do that which he believes impossible, I could not think it possible to change his Life, untill I had first shewn him the Impiety of his Faith, for I should think all my Labours would be to no purpose till I had done this, for should I ask a bold daring Sinner
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:100985:55"/>why he did blaspheme God, who could as easily speak him into nothing as he had at first created him out of it, should I represent to him his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, in thus requiting his best Friend, and choicest Benefactor, and ask him, what made him so insensible of the Mercies and Favours of the Almighty: As thus by a wicked Life and impenitent Heart to Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Happiness, if I ask him why he is so fond of momentary Pleasures, as for the injoyment of them to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon eternal Pains? If I ask him, why he doth not repent of his evil Life that he may dye a happy Death.</p>
            <p>To all this he may truly say; <hi>Alass Sir! What I have done I was Predestinated too, and you know we poor Mortals cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scind the Decrees of Heaven; but are obliged both to do and suffer what God pleaseth to Decree us to, so that whatever difference God may as to our final Interest, make
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:100985:55"/>between us, yet you as well as I, have done only what you was neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitated to. I have as great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to live</hi> according to God's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd Will <hi>as you; but woe is me I cannot, so that whatever I have done contrary to my Reputation in this World, or to my Interest in the next, is not to be imputed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fault of my Will or Life, and I cannot but admire that you belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as I do, should exhort me to Prayer and Repentance, when you know I cannot do what you desire.</hi> And this shall lead me to the last thnig proposed, <hi>viz.</hi> To give such an account of the Divine Decrees as may enable others to avoid those im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Principles which the Thief had imbibed.</p>
            <p>How destructive it is to true Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, to allow Men that they do <hi>the Will of God,</hi> when they live Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously hath been already shewn; as also how unreasonable it is to punish Men for the Commission of those
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:100985:56"/>Sins which they cannot avoid, that therefore I may not oppose the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinistical</hi> Opinion concerning the Divine Decrees, without offering at least what I think more for the glory of God and good of Man, which that I may do, I shall give a short account of what I take to be the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of Divines concerning God's Method of saving Sinners, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God sent his Son into the World to save it, and that our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saviour did by his Death and Sufferings prevail with his Father to pardon our disobedience in our first Parents, and to give us eternal Life through his Merits, and this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life which he purchased for us, was of such a nature that we could not forfeit it but through our own fault: So that tho' we do not believe with the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> that we could <hi>in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris naturallibus</hi> go to Heaven, yet we do not with the <hi>Calvinists</hi> think that we are by any Decree excluded thence, but are perswaded that if we
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:100985:56"/>be not wanting to our selves, that we may as we are commanded, work out our Salvation with fear and trembling. For so good a God we serve, that he hath not only redeemed us with the Blood of his Son, but also given us Grace to receive the benefit of it, insomuch, that if we now perish, after our blessed Saviour hath done and suffered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much to purchace Salvation for us, we are not to impute our Destruction to our want of sufficient Grace to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us to do what we are required; but to our own neglect of those means of Grace which God hath given us, for tho' we are through the Merits of Christ, put into a State of Salvation, yet we are not so certainly secured in it, but that we may loose it unless we make it our care and endeavour to attain it, for tho' we are put in a capacity of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying Heaven, and tho' our blessed Saviour dyed to bring us there, yet if we do not endeavour to attain this
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:100985:57"/>Happiness, we may miss it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sentence of Condemnation, because we have neglected so great Salvation, God hath been so far from excluding any Man from the Kingdom of Heaven by any absolute Decree, that he hath made our way thither, not only possible, but also easie; and if it doth not appear to be our Interest and Happiness, as well as Duty to live religiously, 'tis because we are drawn away by our own Lusts and enticed, because pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent ensnaring Objects make us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of our everlasting Happiness; which being not seen by the Eye of Men, they suffer their Sense to be too hard for their Faith, and are thereby carried away by the love of this World, to the neglect of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in the next. But that Men do this is not imputed to their want of Grace sufficient to do what they are commanded, but to their great neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of their true Interest; and this hath been sufficiently proved by both
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:100985:57"/>Fathers, and Councils: Some of whose Testimonies I would produce, but that I know the Men whose Opinions I oppose, are to proud to value any Authority but their own, and therefore I shall only offer some Texts of Scripture, to prove that God hath given sufficient Grace to all Men, whereby they may work out their Salvation and gain Heaven, and therefore are not excluded either from Holyness or Happiness by any Absolute Immutable or Unconditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Decree, and the first Text that I shall make use of is taken from the 7th Chapter of <hi>the Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> and the 51th verse, where the Apostle doth call those who resisted the holy Ghost, <hi>Stiff-necked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumcised,</hi> telling them <hi>that they as well as their Fore-Fathers did always resist the holy Ghost.</hi> Now if these persons to whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> writ, had not had sufficient Grace given them to receive his Inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, why doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> blame them
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:100985:58"/>for their not doing that, that was not in their power to do; and therefore ought not to be imputed to them as a fault.</p>
            <p>Had this Doctrine of the <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> been either believed or taught in the Apostles time, when St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> did exhort their Followers to continue in the Grace of God. How easily might they have Answered, <hi>Alass! Gentlemen, it is not in our power to do what you exhort us to, God hath not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us Grace sufficient to do what he commanded, for God hath from all eternity Predestinated us to live as we do, and we may sooner shake the Foundations of the Earth, than change the Decrees of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> Which Reply may evidence that this Doctrine of sufficient Grace being given by God to all Men, is no new <hi>Hypothesis</hi> of mine invented to destroy the <hi>Calvinistical</hi> Notion of an Absolute, Immutable, and Unconditional Decree, but is indeed
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:100985:58"/>the Doctrine of the Scriptures, as is evident from these following Texts, <hi>viz.</hi> the 12th Chapter <hi>of the 2d Epistle of</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and the 7th verse, where we read <hi>that St.</hi> Paul <hi>(upon his having a Thorn in the Flesh that he might not be exalted above measure through the abundance of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations)</hi> prays in the 8th verse, <hi>That the Thorn might depart from him.</hi> In Answer to which pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, God tells him in the 9th verse, <hi>that his Grace was sufficient for him.</hi> To this so plain and possitive a Text it may even seem superfluous to offer any farther proof, yet that I may leave this great Truth the more undoubted, I shall offer two Texts more, which in my judgment do evidently prove this Doctrine of sufficient Grace. And the next that I shall offer is taken out of the 23th Chapter <hi>of the Gospel of</hi> St. <hi>Mathew</hi> and the 37th verse, where our blessed Saviour doth with much
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:100985:59"/>compassion bewail the obstinacy of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> saying, <hi>O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou who killest the Prophets, and stonest them who are sent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy Children toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a Hen gathereth her Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens together and ye would not.</hi> By which words our Saviour doth declare his willingness to save those who did desire his Salvation. It would be almost endless to Cite all the kind Invitations which are given to encourage our living Religiously, and to prove our having sufficient Grace to do it, without which all encouragements would seem but as so many delusions and abuses of the Divine veracity, and therefore I shall add but one Text more (least I should rather seem to cloy the <hi>Reader,</hi> than to prove a Truth in its self evident to all, but those, whose Lust and Pride are to hard for their Reason and their Conscience) and that is taken from <hi>the first Fp. of</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:100985:59"/>the 2d Chapter and the 4th verse, in which St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us in words as plain as words can be spoken in, <hi>That God will have all Men to be saved, and to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> So far is our blessed Saviour from desiring our Death and Destruction, that he <hi>Wills</hi> all Men to be saved; what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son have we then to espouse such Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines? which can serve no end of Piety, but tends rather to overthrow it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> tho' the Doctrines I have here endeavoured to expose do carry in themselves their own Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and tho' such is their Impiety, that they need but be named in order to their being abominated, yet so far do some Men's Names even consecrate the vilest Principles, as to make them pass for the best Doctrines; otherwise those Men would never have been thought the greatest propagators of the Gospel, whose Religion was a shame to it.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine of an Absolute, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable and Unconditional Decree, hath in my judgment made more <hi>Athiests</hi> and <hi>Diests</hi> than any Philosophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Principles whatsoever, which makes
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:100985:60"/>me think our <hi>Atheists</hi> have taken their disbelief of a God, from the ill Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter given of him by the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> they thinking the Notion of an Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Power without an equal goodness to be the Description of a Friend, rather than a God, thought it more reasonable to reject the belief of a Being above themselves, rather then to acknowledg such an one whose Honor and Glory they were taught consisted in his making Man only to destroy him, this may make them deny his Being, who was so willing to shew his Power in destroying theirs. It being natural to a Man, not only to wish, but also endeavour to rid himself of those Persons and Things which he finds hurtful to him, and it being easie to believe what one doth desire, such Men as our <hi>Atheist</hi> generally are, may let any shew of an Argument make them conclude against the Notion of any Being which may hinder the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of their so much beloved Wine and Women.</p>
            <p>If different Opinions concerning God and Religion, have made many almost turn <hi>Athests,</hi> I cannot wonder
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:100985:60"/>that the <hi>Calvinistical</hi> Opinions should make Men turn <hi>Deists.</hi> For that it is much more reasonable to believe no <hi>Reveal'd Religion</hi> at all, than such an One, which makes God destroy the <hi>Works of his Hands,</hi> and makes his own <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Institutions</hi> useless; for I cannot understand to what purpose 'tis to prescribe us Laws to walk by, or to appoint Men to teach these Laws, or to be angry with the Devil for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading us to break them, since ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to these Mens Principles, God's own Decrees have made the Teachings of the one and the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the other useless.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Reader,</hi> you may see how <hi>Calvinism</hi> doth occasion both <hi>Atheism</hi> and <hi>Deism,</hi> thoughts of which hath accasion'd these Reflections on the <hi>Fur Praedestinous,</hi> and not any disre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to the Teachers of it; for I hope all Men of any Charity will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that one Man may innocently reflect upon the extravagant Opinions of another, without any hatred against his Person.</p>
            <p>What account can be given of these Decrees I know not, but am sure that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:100985:61"/>all that I have Read have not inclin'd me to believe them true, but I and thousands more do deem them rather a reproach to Christianity, then a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of it, and so vile do I esteem it, that I know not what its Abettors can propose by their Teaching it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it be underhand to do the Devil service, by endeavouring to make God and Religion odious: For how is it possible for any Man to love that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who designs to destroy him, or to practice that Religion in this Life, which will do him no good in the next.</p>
            <p>In fine, this Religion destroys all before it, even that Piety which it pretends to Teach, and that Grace of God which it seems to Magnifie, for it is a Religion as much unfit to be Taught, as it is to be Believed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100985:61"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>